Guide to the D. Michael Quinn Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
D. Michael Quinn papers
1910-2013
1960-2013
WA MSS S-2692
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
127.59
(198 boxes)
The papers document the life and work of D. Michael Quinn, and include research files, writings, personal correspondence, photographs, and family documents. Research files consist of Quinn's notes, as well as copies and transcripts of primary sources that informed many of Quinn's writings on Mormon history, focusing on Church governance, plural marriage, sexuality and gender relations (especially same-sex relationships), and the involvement of Church members in business and politics. Writings include drafts of articles, lectures, and books by Quinn. Other material includes reviews of Quinn's work and other writings about Quinn. Personal papers document the professional and personal life of D. Michael Quinn from the 1950s to the 2000s.
Quinn, D. Michael, 1944-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from D. Michael Quinn on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana and the Arthur Corbitt Hoskins Memorial Fund, 1988-2008.
Conditions Governing Access
Boxes 9-30, 36-37, 39-41, 46-61, 84-85, 88-94, 98-198: Restricted during the lifetime of D. Michael Quinn. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Box 62 (original computer disk): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Boxes 11, 43, 58, 59, 82, 89, 96, 99, 105, 107, 114, 152 (audiovisual material): Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of the collection are available on microfilm, as noted on folder labels.
D. Michael Quinn (born 1944)
D. Michael Quinn (born March 26, 1944) is a historian who specializes in the history of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints (also known as the Mormon Church or LDS). As a young man, Quinn served for two years on a Latter-day Saints Church mission in England. After graduating from college, he served for three years in the U.S. Army. Quinn received a Ph.D. in History from Yale University in 1976. He taught at Brigham Young University from 1976 until he resigned in 1988. In September 1993, Quinn, along with five other Mormon writers, was excommunicated by the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints. His many publications focus on the history of LDS Church governance and organization, sexuality and gender relations (especially same-sex relationships), and plural marriage.
Scope and Contents
The papers document the life and work of D. Michael Quinn, and include research files, writings, personal correspondence, photographs, and family documents. Research files consist of Quinn's notes, as well as copies and transcripts of primary sources that informed many of Quinn's writings on Mormon history, focusing on Church governance, plural marriage, sexuality and gender relations (especially same-sex relationships), and the involvement of Church members in business and politics. Writings include drafts of articles, lectures, and books by Quinn. Other material includes reviews of Quinn's work and other writings about Quinn. Personal papers document the professional and personal life of D. Michael Quinn from the 1950s to the 2000s.
Arrangement
Organized into thirteen groupings: I. October 1988 Acquisition. II. September 1989 Acquisition. III. June 1991 Acquisition. IV. February 1992 Acquisition. V. October 1992 Acquisition. VI. January 1993 Acquisition. VII. December 1996 Acquisition. VIII. December 1997 Acquisition. IX. February 1999 Acquisitions. X. March 1999 Acquisition. XI. June 2003 Acquisition. XII. February 2007 Acquisition. XIII. October 2008 Acquisition. XIV. January 2014 Acquisition. XV. January 2015 Acquisition. XVI. November 2018 Acquisition.
Material within this collection has been organized by acquisition reflecting the fact that the collection has been acquired in increments over time. Researchers should note that material within each acquisition overlaps with or relates to material found in other acquisitions. For example, correspondence and writings can be found in most of the thirteen groupings. In order to locate all relevant material within this collection, researchers will need to consult each acquisition described in the Collection Contents section.
Researchers should also note that similar material can be arranged differently in each acquisition, depending on how the material was organized when it was received by the library.
Bigamy; Christian gays; Gay couples -- Religious life; Historians -- United States -- Archives; Homophobia -- Religious aspects -- Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints; Homosexuality; Mormon Church; Mormon gays; Mormons; Polygamy; Religion and politics; Sex role -- United States; United States -- Religious life and customs; Utah -- History; Audiotapes; Audiovisual materials; Born digital; Color slides; Electronic documents; Photographic prints; Videotapes; Historians -- United States; LGBTQ resource; Quinn, D. Michael, 1944-; Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints
- October 1988 Acquisition, 1944-1988; 10.89; (29 boxes)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Boxes 9-30: Restricted during the lifetime of D. Michael Quinn.
  General note
  Former call number: Uncat WA MS 98
  Arrangement
  Organized under two headings: Research Files, and Personal Papers (Restricted).
  Scope and Contents
  The acquisition consists of research files, writings, correspondence, diaries, and scrapbooks. Research files include transcripts of primary sources (diaries, correspondence, and church records) housed in the archives of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints. Writings consist of drafts and printed versions of articles and longer works on Mormon history by D. Michael Quinn. Diaries and scrapbooks document the life of D. Michael Quinn from the 1944 to the 1970s.
  - Research Files
    - Research notes and transcripts, typescript, undated; 5 (Box 1)
    - Research notes and transcripts, typescript, undated; 5 (Box 2)
    - Research notes and transcripts, typescript, undated; 6 (Box 3)
    - Research notes and transcripts, typescript, undated; 3 (Box 4)
    - Research notes and transcripts, typescript, undated; 7 (Box 5)
    - Research notes and transcripts, typescript, undated; 6 (Box 6)
    - J. Reuben Clark and the Church, notes, undated; 2 (Box 7)
    - Notes on J. Reuben Clark, 1962-1977; 2 (Box 8)
  - Personal Papers (Restricted)
    Restricted during the lifetime of D. Michael Quinn. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
    - "A marketplace of ideas, a house of faith, and a prison of conformity," draft, autograph manuscript, and printed versions, 1988 (Box 9)
    - "The council of fifty and its members, 1844 to 1945," notes, draft, and printed versions, 1980 (Box 9)
    - Writings of D. Michael Quinn, drafts, 1977-1988; 2 (Box 9)
    - LDS Church Authority and New Plural Marriages, 1890-1904, draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 10)
    - Writings of D. Michael Quinn, drafts, 1972-1984; 4 (Box 10)
    - Reviews of works by D. Michael Quinn, 1983-1984 (Box 11)
    - Talk Back with Bob Larson, "Mormon Magic", Guests: Ed Decker / Bill Schnoebelen, Tape 1, 1988 February 8; 1; 01:00:18; Static can be heard on the tape. (Box 11, Item barcode 39002091393356)
      Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
      KQXI Radio; Denver, Colorado
    - Talk Back with Bob Larson, "Mormon Magic", Guests: Ed Decker / Bill Schnoebelen, Tape 2, 1988 February 8; 1; 00:59:55; A high amount of hiss and static can be heard on the tape. The sound speeds up briefly at the beginning of the tape and again at about 00:59:56. (Box 11, Item barcode 39002091393364)
    - Talk Back with Bob Larson, "Mormon Magic", Guest: Van Hale, Tape 1, 1988 February 9; 1; 00:59:53; Static and a high amount of buzz can be heard on the tape. (Box 11, Item barcode 39002091393372)
    - Talk Back with Bob Larson, "Mormon Magic", Guest: Van Hale, Tape 2, 1988 February 9; 1; 00:59:09; A high amount of hum can be heard on the tape. Static and a high frequency noise can be heard as well. (Box 11, Item barcode 39002091393380)
    - D. Michael Quinn, Sunstone Foundation of Denver, Tape 1, 1988 March 12; 1; 00:49:12; Static and high background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 11, Item barcode 39002091393406)
      This talk was held on the Auraria Campus in Denver, Colorado.
    - D. Michael Quinn, Sunstone Foundation of Denver, Tape 2, 1988 March 12; 1; 00:26:23; Static and high background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 11, Item barcode 39002091393398)
    - J. Reuben Clark and the Church, draft, 1981 (Box 11)
    - "The Mormon Church and the Spanish-American War: An end to selective pacifism," drafts and printed version, 1974 (Box 11)
    - Writings of D. Michael Quinn, drafts and printed versions, 1973-1984; 11 (Box 12)
    - Writings of D. Michael Quinn, drafts and printed versions, 1973-1987; 10 (Box 13)
    - J. Reuben Clark and the Church, draft, 1981; 13 (Box 14)
    - Early Mormonism and the Magic World View, draft, 1985-1986; 8 (Box 15)
    - Writings by D. Michael Quinn, drafts, 1978-1984 (Box 16)
    - Published references to D. Michael Quinn, clippings and photocopies, 1980s (Box 16)
    - "Family relationships in the Mormon hierarchy," Utah State Historical Society, 1975 December 2 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence, incoming and outgoing, 1975-1978; 7 (Box 17)
    - Correspondence, incoming and outgoing, 1979-1981; 8 (Box 18)
    - Correspondence, incoming and outgoing, 1982-1983; 7 (Box 19)
    - "A response to Mormon fundamentalists," typescript, 1973 (Box 19)
    - Correspondence, incoming and outgoing, 1984-1985; 7 (Box 20)
    - Interviews with D. Michael Quinn, typescripts, 1972-1988 (Box 20)
    - Correspondence, incoming and outgoing, 1986; 5 (Box 21)
    - Correspondence, incoming and outgoing, 1955-1974; 15 (Box 22)
    - Student papers of D. Michael Quinn, 1957-1971; 30 (Box 23)
    - Student papers of D. Michael Quinn, 1956-1979; 3 (Box 24)
    - Book of Mormon, annotated by D. Michael Quinn, 1962-1987 (Box 25)
    - D. Michael Quinn's high school yearbook, 1962 (Box 25)
    - Passports, 1963-1970 (Box 25)
    - United States Army yearbook, Fort Bliss, 1960s (Box 25)
    - Personal documents and photographs, 1965-1985; 8 (Box 25)
    - Diaries, 1972-1977; 9 (Box 26)
    - Diaries, 1977-1978 (Box 27)
    - Journal, 1964-1980, typescript, undated; 6 (Box 28)
    - Diary, 1972-1973 (Box 28)
    - Scrapbooks, 1950s-1960s (Box 29 Oversize)
    - Scrapbooks, 1950s-1960s (Box 30 Oversize)
- September 1989 Acquisition, 1974-1988; 2.25; (4 boxes)
  Boxes 36-37: Restricted during the lifetime of D. Michael Quinn.
  Former call number: Uncat WA MS 119
  Organized under two headings: Research Files and Personal Papers (Restricted).
  Research files include transcripts of primary sources from the Brigham Young University archives and elsewhere, and index card files containing notes on diverse topics relating to Mormon history.
  - Research Files
    - Transcripts of diaries, undated; 5 (Box 31)
    - Index card files, undated (Box 32)
    - Index card files, undated (Box 33)
    - Index card files, undated (Box 34)
    - Index card files, undated (Box 35)
  - Personal Papers (Restricted)
    - Unsorted personal papers, 1968-1988, undated; 18 (Box 36)
    - Unsorted personal papers, 1980s; 9 (Box 37)
- June 1991 Acquisition, undated; 0.42; (1 box)
  - Research files on J. Reuben Clark, undated; 2 (Box 38)
- February 1992 Acquisition, 1987-1988; 0.42; (1 box)
  - Correspondence, incoming and outgoing, 1987-1988; 11 (Box 39)
- October 1992 Acquisition, 1991-1992; 0.21; (1 box)
  The acquisition consists of a draft of My Mormon Path, and personal papers, all dating to the early 1990s.
  - My Mormon Path, draft, typescript, 1992 (Box 40)
  - Photograph of D. Michael Quinn, 1991 (Box 40)
  - University transcripts of D. Michael Quinn, 1962-1976, 1992 (Box 40)
- January 1993 Acquisition, 1980-1987; 0.25; (1 box)
  Former call number: Uncat WA MS 155
  - Appointment calendars, 1980-1987; 6 (Box 41 Oversize)
  - Yale University diploma (December 1996 Acquisition), 1976 (Box 41 Oversize)
- December 1996 Acquisition, 1973-1996; 16.13; (21 boxes)
  Boxes 46-61: Restricted during the lifetime of D. Michael Quinn.
  Former call number: Uncat WA MS 229
  Organized under two headings: Research Files and Writings, and Personal Papers (Restricted).
  The acquisition consists of drafts of Quinn's writings from the 1990s, associated research files, and personal papers that document Quinn's life from the 1960s to the 1990s.
  - Research Files and Writings
    - Research files, 1990s; 15 (Box 42)
    - Audiovisual material related to Mormon history and the writings of D. Michael Quinn, 1990s; 3 VHS video cassettes and 8 audio cassettes
      - The Church Years: Michael Quinn, HIStory, and the Mormon World View, 1995; 1; 01:31:58; Static can be heard on the tape. (Box 43, Item barcode 39002091393273)
      - A Matter of Principle: Polygamy in the Mountain West, 1991; 1 (Box 43)
      - "Gay Mormons", undated; WAMSSS2692_0006; 1; 00:08:41 (Box 43, Item barcode 39002102370302)
      - Production video of A&E broadcast of Mountain Meadows Massacre, for which Quinn was principle on-camera source, undated; WAMSSS2692_0007; 1; 00:57:48 (Box 43, Item barcode 39002102370310)
      - Mormon History, Quinn interview, 1996 May 17; 1; This audiocassette is blank. It has not been digitized. (Box 43, Item barcode 39002091393281)
      - Beyond the First Presidency: New Plural Marriages in the Church 1890-1904, 1990; 1; 01:30:03 (Box 43, Item barcode 39002091393299)
      - Religion on the Line, 1995 February 12; 1; 01:54:36; The program is distorted at times. High frequency background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 43, Item barcode 39002091393307)
        Guest: Fred Collier, re: Quinn's Origins of Power, KTKK Radio, Salt Lake City, UT
      - "Myth Making and Myth Breaking", panel discussion on D. Michael Quinn's book, Origin of Power, 1995 February 23; 1; 02:00:23; The program is distorted at times. High frequency background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 43, Item barcode 39002091393315)
        B. H. Roberts Society, University of Utah
      - Laboring in the Field: Encountering God in My Profession, panelist D. Michael Quinn, Louis A. Moench, 1996; 1; 01:29:56 (Box 43, Item barcode 39002091393323)
      - The Church Years: Michael Quinn, HIStory, and the Mormon World View, 1995; 1; 01:31:42; Static can be heard on the tape. (Box 43, Item barcode 39002091393331)
      - Your Tithing Dollars at Work: The LDS Church's Political Campaign Against Same-Sex Marriage, panelists Dwight Cook, James Cartwright, Roger Leishman, Jay Stevens, 1996; 1; 01:29:09; A high amount of buzz and static can be heard on the tape. (Box 43, Item barcode 39002091393349)
    - "R.G. Dun Rating Books for Utah", undated; 1 microfilm reel (Box 44)
    - "Agrippa von Nettesheim", undated; 1 microfilm reel (Box 44)
    - Organizational Development and Social Origins of the Mormon Hierarchy, 1832-1932: A Prosopographical Study, 1973 (Box 44)
    - "Research on corporations and businesses involving Mormon hierarchy", undated; 5 (Box 45)
    - "Ancestral file numbers for LDS general authorities and their ancestors (1830-1996)", undated; 1 computer disk (Box 45)
      Existence and Location of Copies
      Electronic files are available through Access Services (Disk #1).
  - Personal Papers (Restricted)
    - Same-sex Dynamics Among Nineteenth-century Americans: A Mormon Example, typescripts and proofs, 1990s; 18 (Box 46)
    - Interview notes, undated; 7 (Box 47)
    - Writings of D. Michael Quinn, including Same-sex Dynamics Among Nineteenth-century Americans: A Mormon Example, typescripts, 1990s; 10 (Box 48)
    - Same-sex Dynamics Among Nineteenth-century Americans: A Mormon Example, typescripts and proofs, 1990s; 8 (Box 49)
    - "Myth making and myth breaking: A discussion of The Mormon Hierarchy: Origins of Power by D. Michael Quinn," printed version, 1995 (Box 49)
    - Reproductions of photographs printed in Same-sex Dynamics Among Nineteenth-century Americans: A Mormon Example, 1990s (Box 49)
    - Same-sex Dynamics Among Nineteenth-century Americans: A Mormon Example, drafts and other related papers, 1990s; 16 (Box 50)
    - Writings of D. Michael Quinn, drafts, 1960s-1990s; 8 (Box 51)
    - Correspondence, incoming and outgoing, 1990s; 7 (Box 51)
    - Correspondence, incoming, 1990s; 12 (Box 52)
    - Portrait photographs of others by D. Michael Quinn, prints, contact sheets and negatives, 1980s; 16 (Box 53)
    - Desk calendar, 1995 (Box 53)
    - Notes, 1962-1977 (Box 53)
    - "Teenage research papers", 1960s (Box 53)
    - Yale University diploma, 1976
    - Printed material annotated by D. Michael Quinn, undated; 2 (Box 54)
    - Passport, 1980s (Box 54)
    - Photographs, slides, undated; 2 (Box 54)
    - Student evaluations, 1980s (Box 55)
    - Study abroad in Vienna, 1983 (Box 55)
    - G. E. materials, 1980s (Box 55)
    - Western United States at Yale, 1970s (Box 55)
    - "Teenage diary project", undated (Box 55)
    - Teaching material, 1980s; 7 (Box 56)
    - Teaching material, 1980s; 11 (Box 57)
    - Phone Messages, 1980s-1990s; 11 (Box 58)
      - Messages from friends, 1987-1988; 1; 01:33:58; High background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 58, Item barcode 39002091393414)
      - Messages from friends, 1988 June - 1989 July; 1; 01:02:53; High background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 58, Item barcode 39002091393422)
      - Messages from friends, 1989 July - 1990 November; 1; 00:49:31; High background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 58, Item barcode 39002091393430)
      - Messages from friends, 1990 November - 1992 April; 1; 01:34:41; High background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 58, Item barcode 39002091393463)
      - Messages from family & friends, 1992 April - February 1993; 1; 01:34:43; High background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 58, Item barcode 39002091393489)
      - Messages from family & friends, 1993 October - 1994; 1; 02:05:48; High background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 58, Item barcode 39002091393448)
      - Messages, 1995 December - 1996 July; 1; 01:34:33; The program is distorted at times. A high amount of hum can be heard. (Box 58, Item barcode 39002091393455)
      - Messages from family & friends, 1993 February - October 1993; 1; 01:34:35; The program is distorted at times. (Box 58, Item barcode 39002091393471)
      - Messages, 1994 May - 1995 February; 1; 01:34:26; High background noise can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 58, Item barcode 39002091393497)
      - Messages, 1995 February - 1995 December; 1; 01:34:48; High background noise and a high amount of hum can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 58, Item barcode 39002091393505)
      - Messages, 1996 July - December; 1; 00:46:10; The program is distorted at times. (Box 58, Item barcode 39002091393513)
        A note indicates the answering machine broke.
    - "Dinner at Jeanie's," a video documentary by filmmaker Lorette Bayle of a party in Salt Lake City in 1986 of a group of friends, including D. Michael Quinn, WAMSSS2692_0002; 1; 00:47:55; The documentary has a run time of 00:14:16. After that, an episode of the Newhart show is recorded. (Box 59, Item barcode 39002102369957)
    - Photographs, negatives, 1970s-1980s; 7 (Box 59)
    - Correspondence, incoming, 1995; 3 (Box 60)
    - Correspondence, incoming, 1980s (Box 61)
    - Desk calendars, 1980s-1990s; 7 (Box 61)
- December 1997 Acquisition, 1973-1976; 0.42; (1 box)
  Former call number: Uncat WA MS 236
  - Organizational Development and Social Origins of the Mormon Hierarchy, 1832-1932: A Prosopographical Study, typescript, 1973; 4 (Box 63)
- February 1999 Acquisitions, 14.38; (22 boxes)
  Boxes 84-85: Restricted during the lifetime of D. Michael Quinn
  Former call number: Uncat WA MS 244
  Several February 1999 acquisitions are filed together under this heading.
  Research files include photocopies and transcripts of historical documents, including documents from the archives of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints. Index cards contain notes on diverse topics relating to nineteenth and twentieth-century Mormon history. Writings include drafts of articles from the 1990s. Personal papers include records that document D. Michael Quinn's family history.
  - Research Files
    - Index cards, undated (Box 64)
    - Index cards, undated (Box 65)
    - Index cards, undated (Box 66)
    - Index cards, undated (Box 67)
    - Research files on Mormon history, Sections I.A-I.B, undated; 57 (Box 68)
    - Research files on Mormon history, Sections I.B-I.E, undated; 24 (Box 69)
    - Research files on Mormon history, Section I.E, undated; 15 (Box 70)
    - Research files on Mormon history, Section I.E, undated; 63 (Box 71)
    - Research files on Mormon history, Section I.E, undated; 37 (Box 72)
    - Research files on Mormon history, Section I.E, undated; 26 (Box 73)
    - Research files on Mormon history, Sections I.E-I.F, undated; 28 (Box 74)
    - Research files on Mormon history, Section I.F, undated; 5 (Box 75)
    - Research files on Mormon history, Section I.F, undated; 4 (Box 76)
    - Research files on Mormon history, Section I.F, undated; 20 (Box 77)
    - Research files on Mormon history, Sections I.G.1-I.G.6, undated; 25 (Box 78)
    - Research files on Mormon history, Section I.G.6, undated; 12 (Box 79)
    - Research files on Mormon history, Sections I.G.6-I.H.2, undated; 28 (Box 80)
    - Research files on Mormon history, Sections I.H.2-I.I, undated; 30 (Box 81)
    - Research files on Mormon history, Section I.I, undated; 12 (Box 82)
    - A Matter of Principle, PBS National Broadcast, 58:40 (Preview), 1990 November 29; 1; 01:00:35 (Box 82, Item barcode 39002102369940)
    - Index cards, undated; 3 (Box 82)
    - "Locations of possible officiators of new polygamy, 1890-1906," index card file, undated (Box 83)
    - "Mormon polygamy chronology, 1903-1962," index card file, undated (Box 83)
    - "Mormon polygamy chronology, 1829-1902," index card file, undated (Box 83)
    - "Council of fifty," index card file, undated (Box 83)
    - Newspaper references to Quinn, 1980s-1990s (Box 83)
  - Personal Papers (Restricted)
    - Writings of D. Michael Quinn, 1990s; 4 (Box 84)
    - Unsorted personal and family papers, 1950s-1980s; 8 (Box 84)
    - Geneaology files, undated; 4 (Box 85)
- March 1999 Acquisition, circa 1910-circa 1999; 5.5; (9 boxes)
  Boxes 88-94: Restricted during the lifetime of D. Michael Quinn.
  Research files and writings include the writings of D. Michael Quinn dating from the 1980s and 1990s, focusing on the business activities of Mormon leaders, and on plural marriage. Personal papers include Quinn's financial records, photographs, and other papers from the 1990s.
  Former call number: Uncat WA MSS 244
  - Research Files
    - "Post-Manifesto polygamous men," index card file, undated (Box 86)
    - "Businesses with LDS general authorities, 1832-1932," index card file, undated (Box 87)
  - Personal Papers (Restricted)
    - Conference and meeting presentations by D. Michael Quinn, 1990s; 18 (Box 88)
    - J. Reuben Clark and the Church, draft, 1980s (Box 88)
    - Research notes and writings of D. Michael Quinn, 1980s-1990s; 8 (Box 89)